A Guide to the Page County Virginia Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #4148
Page County Virginia Papers 1904-1944, n.d.
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
4148
ca. 2500 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the Library by Roger W. Milbourne of Charles Town, West Virginia, on February 2, 1953.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 2,500 items, ca. 1904-1944, and n.d., compiled by Virginia Strickler Milbourne, and includes genealogical and historical information about Page County, Virginia. The historical information includes Indian settlement and archaeology in the area at the time of the first settlers, Governor Spottswood's expedition into the Valley, the Revolutionary War Period, and information on Page when it was part of other counties-- Augusta, Frederick, Orange, and Spotsylvania Counties--mostly in deed and will books. There is also information on the period of the Civil War, and the late nineteenth and early twentieth century periods: particularly notable is the information on the industry in the area, such as forges and mining. There is also information on the Shenandoah National Park, the Shenandoah Valley Railroad(S. V. R. R.), history of utilities in the Valley, area post office and road history, area property and railroad assessments, and the area's national and state politicians and late eighteenth-early nineteenth century area censuses. The genealogical information includes family histories, with some genealogical charts, of Shenandoah Valley families, particularly the German settlers. Information on area parishes emphasizes those of Baptist or Mennonite origins, as many early German settlers were of these denominations.
In addition, there are muster lists from the Revolutionary War and one from the Civil War ( 35th Battalion of Virginia Volunteers). Maps of the Shenandoah Valley region are included as well, including an extensive one for Massanutten (now George Washington) National Forest. Among the newspaper clippings, there are articles on the historic sites of the area. Photographs of area landmarks are included. The 1904-1906 issues of the "Baptist Outlook" of Charles Town are included, as well as "Our Unfinished Task," a history of the Baptists from their beginnings in Europe to their experiences in America. While not extensive, some information can be found on the history of blacks in the Valley. With the information on the Shenandoah River, the reminiscences of the 1870 flood are notable.
Among the bound volumes, there is a collection of literary materials written or collected by area residents. Also, there are two notebooks consisting of a bibliography of materials for Shenandoah Valley history research. Another notebook which contains notes on Shenandoah Valley history contains gravestone inscriptions from area gravesites.
Container List
- Massanutten
  - Massanutten, 1926-1934; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Massanutten: Churches, 1924-1933; (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Massanutten: Iron Industry, 1929-1933 (Box Box 1)
  - Massanutten: Record Books, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Massanutten: Revolutionary War, 1928-1934 (Box Box 1)
- Page County
  - Page County: Augusta, Frederick, and Orange County Records, 1926-1929 (Box Box 1)
  - Page County: Acts for Establishing Spotsylvania and Orange Counties, 1928-1939 (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: Civil War, 1925-1934 (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: Luray, 1929-1931 (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: "The Pedigree of Page", 1919-1939, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: Post Offices and Roads, 1926-1937 (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: Property and Railroad Assessments (Box Box 2)
  - Page County: Transfer from Frederick to Augusta County, 1925-1931 (Box Box 2)
- Shenandoah Valley
  - Shenandoah River, 1928-1938 (Box Box 2)
  - Shenandoah Valley: Baptist and Mennonite Churches, 1925-1932 (Box Box 2)
  - Shenandoah Valley: Early Parishes, 1926-1933 (Box Box 2)
  - Shenandoah Valley History, 1922-1938; (3 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Shenandoah Valley: Native American Ethnology, 1925-1938; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Shenandoah Valley: Revolutionary War, 1926-1935 (Box Box 3)
  - Virginia Patents, Land Deeds, and Fairfax County Deeds (Lord Fairfax Land), 1926-1929 (Box Box 3)
  - Virginia Place Names, 1920-1933 (Box Box 3)
- Genealogies
  - Blue Ridge People, 1926-1934 (Box Box 4)
  - Family Histories A-N, 1923-1936 (Box Box 4)
  - Family Histories O-Y, 1924-1938 (Box Box 5)
  - Stauffer/Stover, etc., 1925-1944 (Box Box 5)
  - Strickler Family Papers, 1913-1943 (Box Box 5)
- Printed and Bound Volumes
  - "Baptist Outlook," Charles Town, WVA, 1904-1906 (Box Box 5)
  - Historical Notes and Records of Letters, 1924-1939 (Box Box 5)
  - Bound Volumes, 1925-1938, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Commonplace Book, n.d. (Box Box 5)